Finding aid for Bentley Historical Library records, 1919 - 2014
Bentley Historical Library
Bentley Historical Library records
1919 - 2014
1970 - 2002
Bentley Historical Library
Bentley Historical Library.
87245 Bimu C445 2 Ac
79 linear feet
2 oversize boxes
1 oversize folder
3 drawers
33.5 GB (online)
The Bentley Historical Library houses the Michigan Historical collections, which documents the history of Michigan; and the University Archives and Records Program, which maintains the historical record of the University of Michigan. Founded in 1935 as the Michigan Historical Collections, directors of the library include Lewis G. Vander Velde, F. Clever Bald, Robert M. Warner, Francis X. Blouin, Jr., and Terrence J. McDonald. The records include administrative files, correspondence, meeting materials, files on exhibits, archived websites, images, audio-visual media, and documentation of special projects such as the Vatican Archives project.
Periodic additions received (Donor no. 1991 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Bentley Historical Library records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Bentley Historical Library record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records (Grant applications) -- Box 15
Student Academic Records -- Box 39
Administrative records -- Box 79
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Student educational records: FERPA's protection of personally identifiable information in a student's education records ends at the time of a student's death and therefore is a matter of institutional policy. As a courtesy to the families of recently deceased students who were enrolled at the time of death, the University generally will not release information from their education records for five years without the consent of the deceased student's next of kin. Eighty-five (85) years after the date the records were first created, the University will presume that the student is deceased. Thereafter the student's education records will be open. Student records at the Bentley Historical Library are restricted for eighty-five (85) years, but may also be made available upon proof of the death of the student.
Executive records: Records generated by the university's executive officers, deans, directors, department heads, and their designated support staff are restricted for twenty (20) years from the date of their creation.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
The origin of the Bentley Historical Library (BHL) can be traced to two related projects initiated in the 1930s at the University of Michigan. In early 1934, Professor Lewis G. Vander Velde successfully applied for a $700 grant to locate and collect printed material relating to the history of Michigan. Approximately a year later, in November 1935, University of Michigan President Alexander Ruthven appointed a Committee on University Archives and authorized it to gather together the university's historical records. Vander Velde served as secretary to this committee. Space was set aside in the William L. Clements Library for both projects, and Vander Velde, with the assistance of a single graduate student, undertook both projects. In June 1938, the two enterprises moved into three rooms of the newly completed Rackham Building. That same year the Regents named the endeavor the Michigan Historical Collections (MHC). In 1973, the library moved from its quarters in the Rackham Building into the newly completed Bentley Historical Library on the university's north campus. For the first time, the MHC had for a home a facility designed and built for the processing and use of the manuscript and archival materials that it had been collecting for nearly forty years.
In the formative years of the MHC, Vander Velde supervised a surprisingly large staff. Funds from the Works Progress Administration made possible the hiring of a large number of special assistants. In 1939, twenty individuals were packing, processing, and cleaning records as they were collected. Although World War II quickly drained away the funds used to pay these many employees, a great deal of work was accomplished and Vander Velde retained some professional assistance. In 1938 or 1939, Vander Velde hired a full-time assistant primarily to collect historical records. In 1951, he added a permanent printed works librarian to the staff.
In 1947, Vander Velde was appointed chair of the university's history department. To lighten his administrative burden at the MHC, F. Clever Bald was appointed to the newly created post, assistant director. Vander Velde retained the title of director of the MHC until 1960, when he retired and was succeeded by Bald. In 1966 Bald retired and was succeeded by Robert M. Warner. In 1980, Warner resigned as director to become head of the National Archives. Richard Doolen served as acting director until 1981 when Francis X. Blouin, Jr. became the fourth director of the BHL. Blouin served more than thirty years, stepping down in 2013, to be succeeded by Terrence J. McDonald, the former dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts.
In 1979, a separate program for the administration of the university archives was formally established. The University Archives and Records Program (UARP) became a separate division alongside the MHC, which continued to focus on documenting the state of Michigan. Reference services and conservation were reconfigured as divisions providing a structure of four divisions (MHC, UARP, Reference and Access, and Preservation and Conservation) under the broader designation of the Bentley Historical Library (BHL).
In 2004, an addition to the Bentley Historical Library's building was completed. This project increased the storage capacity for the library's collections and provided new offices for staff members of UARP. The new wing's dedication coincided with the publication of The Bentley Historical Library: Its History and Purpose, an in-depth review of the library and its collections.
Francis Blouin also oversaw the creation of the Digital Curation Division in 2011. The unit was given responsibility for implementing solutions for the long-term preservation and management of the library's digital assets. Digital Curation supports the mission of the library's other branches by administering born digital and digitized materials for the University Archives and Michigan Historical Collections and also promoting access to digital archives for Reference and Access Services.
In September 2013 Terrence J. McDonald, former Dean of the university's College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, assumed the directorship of the Bentley Historical Library. Under his leadership, the library hired its first development officer and participated in the university's Victors for Michigan capital campaign. McDonald also oversaw the reorganization of, the library's units in the summer of 2014. The Academic Programs and Collection Development division assumed responsibility for classroom instruction, reference and access services, outreach, and field work at the University of Michigan and around the state. The Curation division rationalized the processing activities of the MHC, UARP and the Digital Curation Division, incorporating procedures for both physical and digital archives, and also assumed responsibility for web archiving and digitization activities.
Directors of the MHC / BHL:
1935-1960 Lewis G. Vander Velde
1960-1966 F. Clever Bald
1966-1980 Robert M. Warner
1980-1981 Richard M. Doolen (acting)
1981-2013 Francis X. Blouin, Jr.
2013-2022 Terrance J. McDonald
September 2022- Nancy R. Bartlett (Interim)
The records of the Bentley Historical Library were received in six main accessions 1991, 2000, 2002, 2004, 2007 and 2014. Together the records comprise 79 linear feet, plus two oversize boxes, and oversize folder, three flat file drawers, and more than 16 GB of data spanning the years 1935-2014. The researcher should consult the summary box list on page vii for a quick overview of the materials in the collection.
The records of the Bentley are divided into six subgroups: Administrative Records; Division Records; Outreach: Education, Publicity, and Exhibits; Audio-Visual Material; Architectural Drawings, and Archived Website.
Summary Contents List
Administrative Records
Executive Committee Meeting -- box 1
Friends Meetings -- box 1
Staff Meetings -- box 63
Director's Office/Central Files
Lewis Vander Velde -- Box 2
F. Clever Bald-- Box 2
Robert M. Warner -- boxes 3-4
Richard M. Doolen -- 4
Francis X. Blouin Jr.
(General) -- boxes 6-10, 56-60, 77-78, box 79 [restricted]
Visual Culture and Archives Symposium -- online
Vatican Archives project -- boxes 11-14
William Wallach (Associate Director) -- boxes 50, 61-63
Staff recommendations -- box 15 [restricted]
Non-Donor Correspondence Files
1935-1968 -- boxes 16-18
1961-1987 -- boxes 19-21
1982-2005 -- boxes 21-25
Historical Society of Michigan -- box 64
Division Records
Access and Reference Services -- boxes 26-28
Michigan Historical Collection
Office Diaries --boxes 29-30
Reports -- boxes 31-32, 66-67
Miscellaneous -- boxes 32-33, 65-67, 72-75
Lost and recataloged collections cardfile -- box 68
Preservation and Conservation -- boxes 34-35, 69
University Archives and Records Program
Agendas and Minutes -- box 36
Staff files -- boxes 36-41, 76-77
MeMail project -- box 69 and online
Digital Curation
Papers, strategies, and procedures -- online
Outreach:
Archival Education -- box 42, 70
Press Clippings -- box 42
Exhibits and Art Work -- boxes 43-50, 70
Audio-Visual Material
Publication Production Files -- box 51
Artwork Inventory -- box 52
Photographs -- boxes 53-54, 71
Audiotapes and videotapes -- box 54, 71
Films -- box 55
Architectural Drawings -- drawers 1-3
Digital Materials -- online
Archived Website -- online,
Archives -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Libraries -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Archival institutes and workshops.; North Campus (University of Michigan); Greenland.; Architectural drawings.; Audiotapes.; Digital file formats.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.; Bentley Historical Library.; Michigan Historical Collections.; Warner, Robert M. (Robert Mark), 1927-2007.; Blouin, Francis X.; Vander Velde, Lewis G. (Lewis George), 1890-1975.; Bald, F. Clever (Frederick Clever), 1897-1970.; Catholic Church -- History -- Sources -- Bibliography.; Bentley Historical Library.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies.; Michigan Historical Collections.; Pugh, Mary Jo.; University of Michigan -- Buildings.
- Administrative Records, 1935-2013; 25 linear feet
  The Administrative Records subgroup (1935-2013, 35.5 linear feet) begins with the Meetings series (1956-2012, 1.5 linear feet), which contain the agendas, minutes and correspondence of the Executive Committee Meetings, the Friends of the Michigan Historical Collection and Bentley Library, the Bentley Library's Administrative Committee, and Staff Meetings. The next set of series are organized by director (see the list above). The first subseries category is the Director's Office/Central Files, which are administrative records generated by the director and the associate director including correspondence, evaluation and planning, fundraising, physical facilities documents, and budget materials. The Staff files subseries, contains staff meetings, staff lists, staff interviews, manuals and farewell parties. The Conferences and Events subseries consists of agendas and speeches and planning material from Bentley-related conferences. Materials in this subseries from the tenure of Francis Blouin include digital materials from the Visual Culture and Archives Symposium held April 4-5, 2013 in honor of Blouin's 32 years of service to the library. The Special Projects subseries includes material regarding intensive activities undertaken by the BHL that often were in some way distinct from core functions. In many cases, a "special project" is one that received outside funding.
  - Meetings
    - Executive Committee Meetings
      - December 1956-June 1981 (Box 1)
      - July 1981-April 1988 (Box 1)
      - May 1988-December 1995 (Box 1)
      - 1995-2001 (Box 1)
    - Friends of the Michigan Historical Collection
      - 1968-1972 (Box 1)
      - March 1968-December 1986 (Box 1)
      - November 1986-December 1995 (Box 1)
      - September 1996-October 2003 (Box 1)
      - November 2003-February 2013 (Box 1)
      - Executive Committee Terms, 1972-2004 (Box 1)
      - Minutes, 1981; 1993-2011 (Box 1)
  - Lewis Vander Velde (1935-1960)
    Vander Velde's series contains early material regarding the collecting of university records prior to the formal establishment of the UARP program in 1979.
    - Director's Office/Central Files, 1935-1960
      - Michigan Historical Collection--History (Box 2)
      - Correspondence
        - Campus Offices (Box 2)
        - Committee on University Archives, 1935-1939; 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Executive Committee, 1938-1960 (Box 2)
        - Fundraising Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2)
        - General, 1936 (Box 2)
        - Physical Facilities, 1954 (Box 2)
    - Staff Files
      - Staff Manual circa, 1949 (Box 2)
      - Staff Lists, 1938-1948 (Box 2)
      - Staff Meeting Minutes, 1943-1945 (Box 2)
    - Special Projects
      - American Imprints Inventory, 1938-1940 (Box 2)
      - Chamber of Commerce, 1946 (Box 2)
      - Consumer Cooperatives, 1939 (Box 2)
      - Fraternities (Box 2)
      - Michigan Counties (Box 2)
      - Michigan Legislature (Box 2)
      - Military Camps Publications (Box 2)
      - Monroe (Box 2)
      - National Youth Association (NYA), 1940 (Box 2)
      - Rotary Clubs, 1941-1944 (Box 2)
      - Sparta MI, 1939 (Box 2)
      - Works Progress Association (WPA) Historical Records Survey, 1936-1938 (Box 2)
      - WPA Historical Records Survey, 1939-1942 (Box 2)
      - WPA -- Michigan Writers Project (Box 2)
    - Michigan Historical Collection Talks and Conferences
      - Michigan Historical Collection Talks, 1935-1948 (Box 2)
        - 1935-1943 (Box 2)
        - 1938-1940 (Box 2)
          (Henry D. Brown)
        - 1947-1948 (Box 2)
      - Michigan-Ontario Historical Conference, 1938
      - Lewis Vander Velde Dinner, 1961 (Box 2)
  - F. Clever Bald (1960-1966)
    - Director's Office/Central Files
      - Evaluation Planning Seeking Foundation Support of Michigan Historical Collection of the University of Michigan, 1962 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee, 1960-1966 (Box 2)
      - Physical Facilities Fundraising (Box 2)
      - Physical Facilities General (Box 2)
      - Processing Guidelines (Box 2)
      - Sesquicentennial Celebration Committee, 1964-1967 (Box 2)
      - Willow Run Airport, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Robert M. Warner (1966-1980)
    Warner's series includes documentation of the construction of the Bentley Historical Library in the early 1970s.
    - Director's Office/Central Files
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
        - 1974-1980, 6 folders (Box 3)
        - Vice Provost Academic Affairs, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
      - Fundraising
        - Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
        - Donor Lists (Box 3)
        - Episcopal Room (Box 3)
      - Executive Committee (Box 3)
      - Willow Run Airport, 1970-1977 (Box 3)
      - Physical Facilities
        - Arthur Vandenberg Dedication, 1974 (Box 3)
        - Building File Architects correspondence and memos, 1964-1972 (Box 3)
        - Building Specifications, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Construction Addendum 1-8, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
        - Construction Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
        - Bentley Library Dedication, 1973 (Box 3)
        - Delta Sigma Delta Room Dedication, 1975 (Box 3)
        - Donor Memorial Room Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 3)
        - Fund-raising brochures, 1967 (Box 3)
        - Furnishings, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
        - Groundbreaking and Cornerstone correspondence and documents, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Landscape Plan, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Planning Minutes, 1967-1973 (Box 3)
        - Plans and Sketches, 1969 (Box 3)
        - Prentiss M Brown Room Dedication, 1977 (Box 3)
        - Sculpture, 1973 (Box 3)
        - Correspondence and data on Special Features, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Stack Plans, 1972 (Box 3)
        - Staff Suggestions, 1968-1972; 2 folders (Box 3)
        - Starr Room Dedication, 1977 (Box 3)
        - State of Michigan House Resolution No.319 Tribute to the Dedication of the Bentley Historical Library, 1974 (Map-case 3)
      - Administrative Material (Box 4)
        - Department Organization and Duties (Box 4)
        - Staff Classifications, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
        - Salary Data (Box 4)
        - Statistics, 1962-1978; 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Evaluation Planning and Budget, 1977-1979 (Box 4)
      - Special Projects
        - Alumnae Project, 1977-1979 (Box 4)
        - Atlas Committee (Box 4)
        - Bicentennial Project (Box 4)
        - Book Conservation Workshop, 1978 (Box 4)
        - Conservation, 1980 (Box 4)
        - County Records Survey/Township Records Survey, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
        - Demographic Data, 1968-1971; 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Ethnic Grant, 1973-1979
          - 1973-1974 (Box 4)
          - 1974 (Box 4)
          - Clippings Press Releases, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
          - Quarterly Reports, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
          - Reports on European Fieldwork (Poland) (Box 4)
          - Ethnic Committee (Box 4)
        - Immigration, 1972 (Box 4)
        - Haber Project, 1978 (Box 4)
        - Legislation Libraries (Box 4)
        - NEH Grant Review Committee (Box 4)
        - Records Management Planning Documents (Box 4)
        - Radio Program (Box 4)
        - Temperance and Prohibition Papers -- NHPCR Grant (Box 4)
        - Temperance and Prohibition Papers -- Correspondence (Box 4)
        - Writings by Bentley Staff (Box 4)
      - Topical Files
        - Administration Manual Materials (Box 5)
        - Art Collection, 1978-1982 (Box 5)
        - Audio/Video Reports (Box 5)
        - Bentley Record of Arrangements on Meetings and Programs, 1972-1980 (Box 5)
        - Certification of Archivists (Box 5)
        - Computerized Accessioning System, 1975 (Box 5)
        - Crapo Papers Theft, 1979 (Box 5)
        - Delta Sigma Delta Guest Book, 1975-1985 (Box 5)
        - Gerald Ford Visit, November, 1977 (Box 5)
        - Guest Register (Major Events), 1967-1985 (Box 5)
        - Guide to the Use of the Collections (Box 5)
        - Machine Readable Archives -- CLUBB, 1979 (Box 5)
        - MHC Procedures (Box 5)
        - MHC Public Relations (Box 5)
        - MHC Staff Humor (Box 5)
  - Richard Doolen (1980-1981 Acting)
    - Director's Office/Central Files
      - Correspondence -- Vice Provost and Academic Affairs and Plant Extension, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Francis X. Blouin (1981-2013)
    Among Blouin's records are planning documents that include results of five-year reviews of the library for 1986, 1991, and 1996, and there are a number of files documenting the evolution of archival education at the University of Michigan through the 1980s. There are also papers and correspondence regarding work in 1993, which resulted in a special issue of the American Archivist devoted to diplomacy. Also of interest is documentation of the Vatican Archives Project, which resulted in Vatican Archives, An Inventory and Guide to Historical Documents of the Holy See.
    The 2014 accession of Francis X. Blouin's files is divided into two additional sub-series. The first, Topical Files, 1974-2013 (3.8 linear feet), consists of a mixture of administrative, events and special projects materials, arranged alphabetically. This arrangement reflects how these files had come to be maintained in the director's office. The second, International, 1991-2012 (1.2 linear feet), contains materials related to the library's international programs and is arranged alphabetically by country. Files relating to William Wallach, Associate Director, 1958-2010, bulk 1978-2010, (2.5 linear feet), are arranged in two sub-series: Topical, 1958-2010 (1.5 linear feet) and Building Addition, 1998-2004 (1.0 linear foot).
    - Director's Office/Central Files
      - Administrative Records
        - Budget Material, 1981-82-1995-96, 15 folders (Box 6)
        - Budget Material, 1996-2003; 8 folders (Box 79)
          [Executive records restricted until July 01, 2023 ]
        - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 6)
        - Correspondence-Vice Provost Academic Affairs, 1981-1993 (Box 6)
        - Collection Analysis Project (Judith Endelman), 1986 (Box 6)
        - Evaluation and Planning
          - Archival Management System, 1990 (Box 6)
          - AV Reports, 1982-1984; 2 folders (Box 6)
          - Computerization, 1987 (Box 6)
          - Electronic Records Evaluation (Hedstrom), 1996 (Box 6)
          - Equity Study / Salary Study, 1982-1991 (Box 6)
          - Fire Suppression System, 1985 (Box 6)
          - Five Year Reviews, 1986; 1991; 1996 (Box 6)
          - Appraisal System for Modern Documentation, 1988 (Box 6)
          - McGregor Fund, 1986-1990 (Box 6)
          - Nancy's Reference Review featuring Outlines, Forms and Fun Information, circa 1987 (Box 6)
          - Program Review by Outside Consultants (Frank Burke and Edwin C. Bridges), March, 1987 (Box 6)
          - Report of Activities, 1996 (Box 6)
      - Research Fellowship Program for the Study of Modern Archives sponsored by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation (Box 7)
        - 1983-1986, 44 folders (Box 7)
        - 1987-1988, 26 folders (Box 8)
      - A Decade of Sponsored Research publication, 1994 (Box 8)
      - Topical Files
        - Administrative Committee Decision Logs, 2001 (Box 79)
        - Advisory Committee on Culturally Unidentifiable Human Remains under NAGPRA, 2009-2010 (Box 56)
        - Annex, 1975-1987 (Box 56)
        - Annual report planning, 1974-2009 (Box 56)
        - Archives, Documentation and Social Memory Authors Permissions, 2001-2006 (Box 56)
        - Athletic archivist, 2010-2011 (Box 56)
        - Audio conversion project, 2012 (Box 56)